Guide to the Francis John Anscombe Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Francis John Anscombe Papers
1950-1985
MS 1609
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6
The papers consist primarily of writings and teaching files which document the professional career of Francis Anscombe.
Anscombe, Francis John
Conditions Governing Access
Teaching Files are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Statistics Department in 1991.
Biographical / Historical
Francis John Anscombe was born in Elstree, England on May 13, 1918. He received his B.A. degree from Cambridge University in 1939, and his M.A. degree in 1943. Anscombe was with the British Ministry of Supply from 1940-1945, and the Rothamsted Experimental Station from 1945-1947. He was a lecturer in math at Cambridge from 1948-1956, and a research associate, associate professor, and professor at Princeton from 1953-1963. Anscombe joined the faculty of Yale as a professor of statistics in 1963.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist primarily of writings and teaching files which document the professional career of Francis Anscombe.
Statistics -- Study and teaching; Anscombe, Francis John; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Dept. of Statistics
- Inventory, 1950-1985; 6 linear feet (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Received from: Department of Statistics, 1991 Jun 14
  These papers have been kept in the order in which they were received, and the original folder titles have been retained and/or expanded. The folders contain materials such as drafts of and letters and notes concerning the papers named in the following listing; the actual folder titles often refer to the event or publication for which a particular paper was written.
  - "Normal Likelihood Functions" or "Reduction of Likelihood Functions and Posterior Distributions to Approximately Gaussian Form," F. J. Anscombe, 1963-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Testing binomial response, 1964 March 3 (Box 1)
  - Relation, 1964 June 9 (Box 1)
  - Conference on the Implications of Developments in the Communication Sciences for Legal Education in the Next Decade, at Yale Law school, 1963, 1963, 1965, undated (Box 1)
  - "Bayesian Inference Concerning Many Parameters, With Reference to Supersaturated Designs," F. J. Anscombe, 1962-1965, undated (Box 1)
  - "Pre-decisional Processes Related to Psychophysical Judgement," Emir H. Shuford, 1963 March 25, undated (Box 1)
  - "Comments on Kurtz-Link-Tukey-Wallace Paper," F. J. Anscombe, 1964, undated (Box 1)
  - "Some Principles of Estimation," F. J. Anscombe, 1960, 1964-1965, 1969, undated (Box 1)
  - "An Analysis of Transformations," G. E. P. Box and D. R. Cox, 1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Classification problem, 1965, undated (Box 1)
  - "Treatment of Outliers in Samples of Size Three," paper by F. J. Anscombe and Bruce A. Barron for the Journal of Research of the National Bureau of Standards, 1965-1966, undated (Box 1)
  - "Topics in the Investigation of Linear Relations fitted by the Method of Least Squares," paper/drafts by F. J. Anscombe for Research Section, 1966 (2 folders), 1965-1967, undated (Box 1)
  - "Statistical Analysis, Special Problems of: Outliers," article by F. J. Anscombe for the International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, 1960-1968, 1975, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers concerning outliers, residuals, etc., 1966, 1973, undated (Box 1)
  - "Graphs in Statistical Analysis," F. J. Anscombe, 1971-1974, 1976, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Loose papers, 1966, 1969-1971, undated (Box 1)
  - International Institute of Statistical Computing, M. E. Muller, Director, 1962, 1969-1970, undated (Box 1)
  - Materials concerning a discussion of Bayesian and non-Bayesian decision theories led by Professors Savage and LeCam at the 1964 annual meeting of the Institute of Mathematical Statistics in Amherst, 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - "Some Remarks on Bayesian Statistics," paper by F. J. Anscombe and other materials concerning the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1961-1964, undated (Box 2)
  - The Seventh Conference on the Design of Experiments in Army Research, Development, and Testing, 1961-1962, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes on "An Introduction to the Frequency Analysis of Time Series," J. W. Tukey, 1963 (Box 2)
  - "A Definition of Subjective Probability," F. J. Anscombe and R. J. Aumann, 1961-1963, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Examination and Analysis of Residuals," F. J. Anscombe and J. W. Tukey, 1961, undated (Box 2)
  - "Sequential Medical Trials," F. J. Anscombe, 1960-1964, undated (Box 2)
  - "Tests of Goodness of Fit," F. J. Anscombe, 1962-1963, undated (Box 2)
  - The Sixth Conference on the Design of Experiments in Army Research, Development and Testing (at the Aberdeen Proving Ground, Maryland), 1960-1962, undated (Box 2)
  - "Examination of Residuals," F. J. Anscombe (2 folders), 1960-1962, 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Memos concerning the authorship of the Federalist Papers, 1959-1961 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1961, undated (Box 2)
  - "Some Recommendations for Statistical Quality Control of Electricity Meters Based on Sample Testing," Anna M. Glinski and Mary G. Natrella, 1961 August 30 (Box 2)
  - "Testing Meters on a Statistical Quality Control Basis," Commonwealth Edison Company, undated (Box 2)
  - "Estimating a Mixed-Exponential Response Law," F. J Anscombe, 1959-1962, undated (Box 2)
  - "Rectifying Inspection of a Continuous Output," F. J. Anscombe, 1957-1959, 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - "Rectifying Inspection of Lots," F. J. Anscombe, 1950, 1958-1962, 1964, undated (Box 3)
  - "Quick Analysis Methods for Random Balance Experiments," F. J. Anscombe (3 folders), 1955, 1958-1959, undated (Box 3)
  - "Bayesian Statistics," F. J. Anscombe, 1959-1961, 1963-1965, undated (Box 3)
  - "Testing to Establish a High Degree of Safety or Reliability," F. J. Anscombe, 1960-1962, undated (Box 3)
  - Continuous Sampling, 1957, undated (Box 3)
  - Leonard J. Savage, notes, 1959-1960, undated (Box 3)
  - Trenchard More. Jr., theorem proving, 1957, 1960, 1966, 1969, undated (Box 3)
  - John Wiley & Sons, Inc. Publishers, 1979-1980, undated (Box 3)
  - "'ASP': A Statistical Package in APL," appendix to Statistical Computing with APL, F. J. Anscombe, 1973, 1976-1977, undated (Box 3)
  - Statistical Computing with APL, draft of first nine chapters, notes, and appendices (2 folders), 1970, 1972, undated (Box 3)
  - Statistical Computing with APL, miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - Jerzy Neyman at the University of Connecticut at Storrs, 1977, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence re: APL, 1970, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Technical Report No. 32, "Tests of Residuals in the Additive Analysis of a Two-way Table - A Suggested Computer Program," F. J. Anscombe, Diccon R. E. Bancroft, and William J. Glynn, 1974, 1979, undated (Box 3)
  - International Symposium on Statistical Ecology, Yale University, August 21-28, 1969, 1969-1970, undated (Box 3)
  - "Directions of statistical Research," F. J. Anscombe, 1977, undated (Box 3)
  - Materials for APL Short Course, 1971-1972, undated (Box 3)
  - Loose papers, 1968, undated (Box 3)
  - "Use of Iverson's Language APL for Statistical Computing," F. J. Anscombe, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
  - Papers for the Ninth Annual Phi Delta Kappa Symposium on Educational Research Methods, Syracuse, New York, 1968 Jan 12, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - "Rejection of Outliers," F. J. Anscombe, 1959-1960, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Le Meilleur Procédé pour l'Inspection Rectifiante d'un Lot, F. J. Anscombe, 1953, 1954, undated (Box 4)
  - "Towards a Theory of Statistical Inference," F. J. Anscombe (3 folders), 1953, 1958, undated (Box 4)
  - "Dependence of the Fiducial Argument on the Sampling Rule," F. J. Anscombe, 1957, undated (Box 4)
  - "Queueing Theory," F. J. Anscombe, 1958-1961, undated (Box 4)
  - "Notes on Sequential Sampling Plans," F. J. Anscombe, 1956, 1959-1960, undated (Box 4)
  - "Contribution to Discussion of Paper by C. A. B. Smith," F. J. Anscombe, 1960, undated (Box 4)
  - "Duncan on Multiple Comparisons,", undated (Box 4)
  - Papers written and translated by G. Taguchi, 1963, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Nature of Statistical Inference," Arthur P. Dempster, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Papers for the Actuarial Research Conference on Risk Theory and Topics in Multivariate Analysis, 1966, 1967, undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence concerning the Twenty-Fourth Annual Princeton Conference of the American Society for Quality Control, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Memo concerning the "Pittsburgh Meetings", 1968 March 18 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and other materials concerning the Eastern Regional Meeting of the Institute of Mathematical Statistics, held at the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Blacksburg, Virginia, 1968 Apr 8-10, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with and papers for DuPont, 1969 undated (Box 4)
  - "Regression Analysis in the Computer Age," F. J. Anscombe, presented to the Thirteenth Conference on the Design of Experiments in Army Research, Development, and Testing, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and other materials regarding the Research Conference on Mathematical and Statistical Techniques Applicable to Actuarial Problems, 1966-1968, undated (Box 4)
  - Unsigned note regarding orthogonal polynomials, 1967 July 21 (Box 4)
  - Untitled, unsigned notes for the Barden Corporation, undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence about and papers for the Symposium on Clinical Therapeutic Trials, Paris, 1969 Sep 15-17, 1965-1969 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence regarding the Committee on Computers in Statistics, American Statistical Association (ASA), 1967-1969 (Box 5)
  - ASA Committee on Computers in Statistics meeting in New York, 1969 Aug 19-22 (Box 5)
  - Conference on Statistical Computation, Madison, Wisconsin, 1969 Apr 29 (Box 5)
  - Statistical Language Workshop, San Francisco, 1969 Jun 23-27, 1968, 1969, undated (Box 5)
  - Summer workshop on the Instructional Use of Computers in Statistics, at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1969 (Box 5)
  - IBM New York Scientific Center Second Annual Symposium on Statistical Computation, New York, 1968 Dec 16-17, 1968-1969, undated (Box 5)
  - Computer Science and Statistics, Fourth Annual Symposium, University of California at Irvine, 1970 Sep 17-18, 1970, undated (Box 5)
  - "Experiments in Computer Oriented Instruction in Statistics," proposal submitted to the National Science Foundation (NSF), 1970-1971, undated (Box 5)
  - 1970 Annual Meeting of the ASA, Detroit, 1969, 1970, undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with the Naval Ship Research and Development center, 1969-1970, undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with the Naval Underwater Systems Center, 1973, undated (Box 5)
  - "Research in Basic Concepts and Analytic Methods of Statistics," F. J. Anscombe, and other materials prepared for the Office of Naval Research (2 folders), 1964-1981, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Teaching files
    Conditions Governing Access
    The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
    - Statistics 165b, 1970 (Box 5)
    - SS10/Statistics 23c, Summer 1977 (Box 5)
    - Summer Terms 1975, 1977, 1974-1977 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 41a, Fall 1964 (Box 5)
    - General Examination in Statistics, 1979 January 8 (Box 5)
    - General Examination in Statistics, 1972 May 11-12 (Box 5)
    - General Examination in Statistics, 1971 May 13-14 (Box 5)
    - General Examination in Statistics (grading sheet), 1970 (Box 5)
    - General Examination in Statistics, 1969 May 15 (Box 5)
    - General Examination in Statistics, 1968 May 17 (Box 5)
    - General Examination in Statistics, 1967 May 18 (Box 5)
    - General Examination in Statistics, 1966 May 19 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 110a, Fall 1970 (Box 5)
    - History 690a, Fall 1986 (Box 5)
    - General Examination in Statistics, 1965 May 19 (Box 5)
    - ISS 384, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 199, Fall 1972 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 125b, Spring 1976 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 111b, Spring 1967 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 101b, Spring 1971 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 150a, Fall 1964 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 155b, Spring 1971 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 101, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 101, Fall 1968 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 209, Fall 1968 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 209/History 299 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 47a, Fall 1967 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 42b, Spring 1966 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 42a, Fall 1971 (Box 5)
    - Statistics 42b, Spring 1967 (Box 6)
    - Statistics 42b, Spring 1965 (Box 6)
    - Statistics 230a, Fall 1974 (Box 6)
    - Statistics 41b, Spring 1973 (Box 6)
    - Statistics 41b, Spring 1974 (Box 6)
  - Committee to Visit the Department of Statistics, Harvard College, 1978-1985, undated (Box 6)
  - The ASA Committee on Fellows, 1979-1984, undated (Box 6)
  - Harvard-Yale Statistics Day ("Talk: How far to go on looking at data"), 1980 November 21 (Box 6)
  - IBM's APL on the PC-AT keyboard, 1986 January 31, undated (Box 6)
  - "Hardcopy for APL," F. J. Anscombe, 1984, undated (Box 6)
  - Ed Shaw and the New York Local Chapter of the Special Interest Group on APL of the Association for Computing Machinery, 1972, 1984 (Box 6)
  - A review of Simultaneous Statistical Inference by F. J. Anscombe by Rupert G. Miller, Jr., 1981, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Two papers by and correspondence with Clifford C. Clogg, 1982-1983, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence regarding Statistical Science, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
  - The Thirty-Eighth Annual Conference on Applied Statistics, the American Society for Quality Control, 1982, undated (Box 6)
  - Rothamsted Experimental Station, 1968, 1971, 1977, 1979, undated (Box 6)
  - Trip to England, Miscellaneous, 1979, undated (Box 6)
  - Review by F. J. Anscombe of Statgraphics, 1985, undated (Box 6)
  - Symposium in Honor of J. W. Tukey, 1985 May (Box 6)
  - Review by F. J. Anscombe of Residuals and Influence in Regression, by R. Dennis Cook and Sanford Weisberg, 1982, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Statistics Panel of the Conference Board of the Mathematical Sciences (CBMS) Research Vitality Planning Project Committee, 1978-1981, undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence regarding APL(*)PLUS, 1985, undated (Box 6)
  - Connecticut Chapter of the ASA, 1980, 1982-1983, undated (Box 6)
  - Undergraduate Mathematics and its Applications Project (UMAP), 1979 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Lincoln Moses, Department of Energy, 1963, 1978 (Box 6)
  - "How far to go in looking at data," F. J. Anscombe, keynote address for the 26th Conference on the Design of Experiments in Army Research, Development and Testing, 1980, undated (Box 6)
  - "Partial Likelihood Methods in Transformation Models," Kjell M. Doksum, 1954, 1985 (Box 6)
  - New England Regional Computing Program (NERComP) Conference on Statistical Methods, 1979, undated (Box 6)